Guide to the Temple Beth-El records, 1919-2002.
Temple Beth-El records
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Temple Beth-El records, 1919-2002.
3834
Temple Beth-El (Ithaca, N.Y.)
5.0 cubic ft.
Correspondence, Financial documents, Photographs, Printed materials, Publications
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Material pertaining to the founding, meetings, worship, and activities of the temple, a congregation in the United Synagogue of Conservative Judaism.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Minutes, account books, lists, financial statements, correspondence, publications and other material pertaining to the founding, meetings, worship, and activities of the temple, a congregation in the United Synagogue of Conservative Judaism. Includes the Temple Beth-El Bulletin. Deeds and documents relating to the building and cemetery, photographs, seals and other items from the Temple are also included.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Temple Beth-El (Ithaca, N.Y.)
Subjects:
Temples -- New York (State) -- Ithaca.; Synagogues -- New York (State) -- Ithaca.; Judaism -- New York (State) -- Ithaca.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.) -- Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Account books.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Temple Beth-El Bulletin
  The name of the bulletin varies. Some editions missing.
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1944 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Temple Beth-El Bulletin, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Various Temple Publications and Files
  - Temple Directories, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Temple's Mortgage, 1968, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Contains copy of October 29,1978 Mortgage, March 1968 Agreement.
  - Ithaca Anti-Semitism Incidents, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes various letters to the editor and articles.
  - Miscellaneous Newspapers, 1983, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes: Iton Ithaca, The Temple Times, The Temple Tribune, The Jewish Theological Society of America News.
  - Rules and Regulations for the Cemeteries; including board resolutions, etc. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes: photos, cemetery deed, plot information, article "The High Cost of Dying" by Ruth Mulvey Harmer, correspondence.
  - History of the Cemeteries: Including Maps and Records (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Construction Specifications and General Conditions for the Addition and Alterations to Temple Beth-El, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Materials previously in binder.
  - Additions and Alterations to Temple Beth-El, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Program report.
  - Obituaries (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Wish List, Memorials, and Miscellaneous Information, 1991, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Includes: Temple Beth-El Wish List, Guide to Congregational Standards, selections from The Reporter.
  - Veterans' Day Service Brochures, 1950-1960 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Temple Beth-El Star, 1942-1943 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Ithaca Community Union Thanksgiving Service Brochures, 1942-1960 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Tercentenary Material (Box 2, Folder 24)
    Includes: brochures, correspondence, and articles regarding the tercentenary of the American Jewish community.
  - Miscellaneous Temple Publications (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Includes: event brochures, correspondence, documents, etc.
  - Publications from the Jewish Theological Society of America, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Includes: "Aspects of Rabbinic Theology" by Solomon Schechter and "The Unseen Powerful Force in Life" by Rabbi Bernard Mandelbaum.
  - Community Reception and Brunch, 1990, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Temple Anniversary Publications, 1978-2003 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Booklets for 1978, 1988, and 2003 anniversaries.
  - Bronze Tablet Plaques Name Plate Pledge Forms (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Pad of blank actual size drawings of name plates for pledges.
- Minutes
  - Board of Trustees Minutes January 26, 1966 to June 21, 1967, 1966-67 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Bound notebook; includes some inserted pages.
  - Board of Trustees Minutes June 21, 1967 to (November 9, 1967), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Bound notebook; includes note on front cover "extensive on addition building".
  - Board of Trustees Minutes 1975, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Photocopies of handwritten and typed pages from a binder.
  - Board of Trustees Minutes 1975-1977, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Handwritten and typed pages from a binder.
  - Board of Trustees Minutes 1977-1980, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Board of Trustees Minutes 1980-1982, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Photocopied typed pages from a binder.
  - Board of Trustees Minutes 1982-1985, 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Board of Trustees Minutes 1985-1987, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Temple Board Meeting Minutes, 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Handwritten and typed pages from a binder
  - Sisterhood Minutes August 1977-June 1983, 1977-1983 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Handwritten pages from a binder
  - Minutes of Women's Auxiliary of Temple Beth-El, 1931-1934 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Bound notebook.
  - Minutes of Women's Auxiliary of Temple Beth-El (Typed), 1931-1934 (1978) (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Typed by Anne G. Kramer, June 1978, in spiral binding.
  - Hebrew Women's Aid Society Minutes, 1919-1924 (Box 5)
    Bound notebook, includes financial records and minutes.
  - Board Meeting Minutes, 1931 (Box 5)
    Bound notebook, spine is detached, papers inserted into book, drawings on inside covers.
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence: Temple Policies, 1964-1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Includes Constitution And Bylaws of Temple Beth-El, various mailings regarding temple policy.
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, Rabbinical Appointments, Activities, 1959-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Rabbinical Society of America (כנסית הרבנים באמריקה), 1953-1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Correspondence sent to Temple Beth-El.
  - New Members Letters, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Copies of letters sent to new members of the temple.
  - Temple Beth-El Correspondence Received, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Miscellaneous Publications
  - Guide to the Jewish Holidays, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Sealable envelope with two plastic rings, opens up to pages with information about several Jewish holidays. Text in Hebrew and English.
  - Make 'em (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Booklet of instructions for craft-making for children, published by the Overseas Youth Department of the Jewish National Fund, Jerusalem.
  - Folk Dances For Jewish Festivals, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Written by Dvora Lapson.
  - Alefbet Coloring Book, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Illustrated by Sigmund Forst.
- Archives concerning Lakeview Cemetery Plots
  Items stored horizontally in box, with one folders and four books.
  - Ithaca Supreme Court Proceedings, Agoodash Achim vs. Temple Beth El/Lakeview Cemetery, March 30, 1932 (Box 4)
    Book in fastened paper binding.
  - Congregation Agudis Achim Book of Minutes, 1933-1941 (Box 4)
    Bound notebook, includes inserted papers.
  - Ledger, 1933-1935 (Box 4)
    Includes Meeting of April 21, 1935, member dues ledger, papers inside cover.
  - Ledger, 1930-1932 (Box 4)
    Front and back covers have been detached from spine.
  - Temple Beth-El Cemetery Fund forms (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Two papers previously in a larger package; reservation for plots.
  - Cemetery Fund forms package (Box 4)
    Can deaccession.
  - Deed - Agoodash Achim to Temple Beth-El, Lakeview Cemetery Plots, April 5, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Includes copy of the deed, memos to Ralph Marvin, and copies of minutes concerning the subject.
- Archives Concerning Temple Fund
  - Cornell Jewish Temple Fund, 1926-1929 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    List of Cash Donations and Pledges, record of paid contributions.
  - Donation and Member Records, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Includes correspondence, receipts of donations, lists of uncollected and collected pledge donations.
  - Contributor Records, 1925-1927 (Box 5)
    Ledger with names and addresses of contributors, and dates and amounts of donations.
  - Cornell Jewish Temple Fund Administrative Account, 1925-1927 (Box 5)
    Ledger with deposits and withdrawals including specific allocations of voucher money.
- Photographs
  - Sieger 6/4/70, June 4, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Includes 24 prints, 36 negatives.
  - Photos, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Includes 33 prints, 19 negatives.
  - Mr. Hecht 4/2/90, April 2, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Includes 49 prints, 37 negatives, sales receipt.
  - Mr. Hecht 4/11/90, April 11, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Includes 19 prints, 16 negatives, sales receipt.
  - Printed Pictures of the Temple, 1963? (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Two photocopies of photographs of the temple, one paper with "G.E Advanced Electronics Center Print From Negative No. 4546 (m), 1963".
  - Fr. Rabbi and TBE Documents (Box 6)
    12 prints.
  - Pictures of Beth-El Synagogue (Box 6)
    11 prints.
  - Relsch 5749 (Box 6)
    51 prints.
  - Purim 1997 (Box 6)
    5 prints, includes envelope marked "Payment enclosed".
  - Teaching Staff '96-'97, 1996-1997 (Box 6)
    7 prints.
  - David Karr (Box 6)
    15 prints.
  - Purim Pictures, Judith and David Tanenbaum 1997 (Box 6)
    32 prints.
  - Mrs. Baines (Box 6)
    5 prints.
  - Other Photos (Box 6)
    3 prints.
  - Community Reception and Brunch, Temple Beth-El, April 1, 1990 (Box 6)
    Photo album, 27 prints.
  - 50th Anniversary Dinner Party (Box 6)
    Box with return address of J.S. Hecht. Includes 19 color slides.
- Artifacts
  - Yad (Box 7)
    Metal rod with chain, hand with pointer finger (detached); used for reading scripture.
  - Scroll, "Psalms of David" (Box 7)
    Facsimile scroll of the Book of Psalms on one roller, with fabric cover marked "Psalms of David". One knob at the end of the roller missing. Text in English.
  - מגילת אסתר (Story of Esther) (Box 7)
    Facsimile scroll of the Story of Esther, includes fabric cover marked "מגילת אסתר Story of Esther", stored in cardboard box. Text in Hebrew.
  - מגילת אסתר (Story of Esther), January 17, 1949 (Box 7)
    Facsimile scroll of the Story of Esther, includes fabric cover marked "מגילת אסתר Story of Esther", stored in cardboard box. Text in Hebrew. Rolled up with flyer for the Matzoh Fund (Text in Hebrew and English) and telegram from Kollel America.
  - Stamps (Box 7)
    Six stamps of varying sizes; three imprinted with the image of Temple Beth-El, one imprinted with image of a lamp, one with image of a menorah, and one with image of a scroll marked "USY"
  - "Official" Pocket Seal (Box 7)
    Metal pocket seal (two parts which fit together); seal reads "Temple Beth-El of Ithaca, NY, Inc. 1924". Includes instruction guide, leather case, identification labels, "The Sigwalt Notary and Corporation Handbook"; stored in "Official" cardboard box.
  - "A Gift from Menorah Chapels...to remember the important celebrations of our faith." (Box 8)
    Information on the holidays of Rosh Hashana, Yom Kippur, Sukkot, Chanukah, and Passover; Drawings of religious objects.
- Audio Media
  - The Early History of Temple Beth-El, May 7, 2003; CD-2045 (Box 7)
    CD Format, return address of Matt Braun.
  - Temple Beth-El 75th Anniversary Program, Audio cassette, May 19, 2003; TR-10081 (Box 7)
- Posters
  - Foam Board Posters, 11" x 11"
    Posters printed with photographs, articles, and other historical documents. Prepared by congregant Matthew Braun, director of the Tompkins County History Center, for the 75th anniversary commemoration event at Temple Beth-El.
  - "Snapshots Of Our Community" by Matthew Braun; description of the panel collection., 2003 (Box 8)
    11" x 11" Board
  - Photo of people crowding around the temple, sign reading "The New Religious School, Expanded Sanctuary Social Hall, Temple Beth El"., 2003 (Box 8)
  - Purim, 1909(?), 2003 (Box 8)
  - Photos, letter, and program of Cornerstone Laying, Sunday August 26, 1928, 3 PM., 2003 (Box 8)
  - Sanborn Fire Insurance Map, 1929-1965, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Article, "The Future Jew and Jewess of Cornell", 2003 (Box 8)
  - Article, "How Proposed Jewish Temple in Ithaca Will Look if the Local Campaign for Funds is Successful; Reasons Given Why Public Should Aid Project", 2003 (Box 8)
  - Pictures of Mr. and Mrs. Nathan Hanford, 1898-99; Letter to Daniel Rothschild from Unitarian Church about donations., 2003 (Box 8)
  - Ithaca Aerial View, 1938, 2003 (Box 8)
  - Foam Board Posters, 24" x 16"
  - Interior of Temple Beth-El, Tioga and Court Streets Ithaca NY, Facing West towards the sanctuary balcony from inside the roof dome., 4-5 March 2005 (Box 8)
    24" x 16" Board. Photo by Richard Jump marking his participation in the Bnai Torah Celebration of Parashah/Shabbat VaYakhel.
  - Interior of Temple Beth-El, Tioga and Court Streets Ithaca NY, Facing East towards the Aron Kodesh from inside the roof dome., 4-5 March 2005 (Box 8)
  - Facing South: The roof dome of Temple Beth-El, Tioga and Court Streets Ithaca NY, 4-5 March 2005 (Box 8)
  - Inside the dome of Temple Beth-El, Tioga and Court Streets Ithaca NY, 4-5 March 2005 (Box 8)
  - Inside the dome of Temple Beth-El, Tioga and Court Streets Ithaca NY (2), 4-5 March 2005 (Box 8)
  - Inside the dome of Temple Beth-El, Tioga and Court Streets Ithaca NY (3), 4-5 March 2005 (Box 8)
  - Inside the dome of Temple Beth-El, Tioga and Court Streets Ithaca NY (4), 4-5 March 2005 (Box 8)
  - Collage Posters
    Posters with attached photographs, articles, and other historical documents.
  - Articles: "Klansman Spells Out His Beliefs in Exclusive Interview", "Klan 'Ideals' Suspect, Anti-Defamation Chief Says", "Teachers to Have Workshop Session", "Teachers Urged to Meet Child's Emotional Needs"; Info and photos of Gertrude Noar, Daniel Rothschild Lodge., 1965; July-December, 1965 (Box 8)
    Certain items highlighted and connected with arrows.
  - "B'nai B'rith Vocational Service"; B'nai B'rith Commission on Israel, Bulletin for February 1966; A.D.L. Guest Speaker Hersh L. Adlerstein; Hillel at Cornell University, Spring 1966; The ADL Bulletin, September 1965, "Are Europe's Jews in Danger?"; B'nai B'rith Adult Jewish Education "Time For Torah"; Leo N. Levi Memorial Hospital, letter from Fannie B. McLaughlin to Mr. Marvin; photo of B'nai B'rith Building, Washington, D.C., 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Daniel Rothschild Lodge 1450 B'nai Birth, Open Meeting for Husbands and Wives, September 21, 1965; "B'nai B'rith To Present Essay Prizes"; "Brotherhood Essay"; "Classes Learn Lessons Of Brotherhood Week"; "Servicemen Write Thanks For Cayugan Each Month"; Tompkins County Mental Health Association, "Breakdown"; "Flower Pots"; Letter of thanks from Ithaca Junior Bowling Council to B'nai B'rith; "Fifteen Institutions Consider The Organization Of New Scout Units"; Inter-Fraternal Council, Ithaca, New York, Members Lists; "Event Honors 17 Inductees"; The Cayugan, 2 March, 1966; Letter from Rabbi Henry E. Barneis to B'nai B'rith Daniel Rothschild Lodge; Daniel Rothschild Lodge 1450 B'nai B'rith meetings, 1965-1966., 1960-1966 (Box 8)
    Certain items highlighted and connected with arrows. Sticky note on back reading "Matt Braun".
- Certificates
  - Award Of Honor for the Sisterhood Beth El Ithaca, given by The Jewish Theological Seminary of America, 1965-1966 (Box 8)
  - Certificate of Membership of Temple Beth-El to The Union of American Hebrew Congregations, March 28, 1949 (Box 8)
  - Charter of Affiliation of Temple Beth-El to The United Synagogue of America, June 4, 1989 (Box 8)
  - State of New York Office of the Secretary of State, Certificate of Incorporation of Temple Beth-El of Ithaca, New York, Inc., August 20, 1924 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Signed by James A. Hamilton.